<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The 4. of November. The peace of France. Or The edict, with the articles of peace, granted by the French king vnto his subiects of the reformed religion. For the establishing of a firme and generall peace throughout the whole kingdome of France Given at his campe before Mompellier the nineteenth day of October. 1622. Faithfully translated out of the French copie.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1622-10-19. English and French</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108845</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844498</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844498</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9315</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06371)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9315)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 845:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The 4. of November. The peace of France. Or The edict, with the articles of peace, granted by the French king vnto his subiects of the reformed religion. For the establishing of a firme and generall peace throughout the whole kingdome of France Given at his campe before Mompellier the nineteenth day of October. 1622. Faithfully translated out of the French copie.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1622-10-19. English and French</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
                  <author>Louis XIII, King of France, 1601-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12; 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] D[awson and Thomas Snodham] for Nathaniel Newbery, and are to be sold at his shop vnder S. Peters Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley at the Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes the original French text with separate pagination and register; this part was printed by Snodham.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9315:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9315:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The 4. of November.</p>
            <p>THE PEACE OF FRANCE. <hi>OR</hi> THE EDICT, WITH THE Articles of Peace, granted by the French King vnto his Subiects <hi>of the Reformed Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the eſtabliſhing of a firme and generall <hi>Peace throughout the whole Kingdome of</hi> FRANCE.</p>
            <p>Given at his Campe before <hi>Mompellier</hi> the nineteenth day of October. 1622.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Faithfully Tranſlated out of the</hi> French
<hi>Copie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I.D.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop vnder <hi>S. Peters</hi> Church in Cornehill, and in <hi>Popes</hi>-head Alley at the Starte. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="Edict_of_Nantes">
            <pb facs="tcp:9315:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9315:2"/>
            <head>THE PEACE OF FRANCE, <hi>OR</hi> THE EDICT, WITH THE
<hi>Articles of Peace; granted by the</hi> French King, vnto his Subiects of the <hi>Reformed Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="preamble">
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>EWIS,</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navare.</hi> To all thoſe which ſhal ſee theſe preſents Greeting. As a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian &amp; Godly Prince which feareth God, ought to abhorre the effuſion or ſhedding of the blood of man, who is created in the Image of God: So is hee likewiſe bound and tyed not onely to ſhunne the occaſions of Civill and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticke warre, for to reunite his Subiects, and to make them liue vnder the Lawes of <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:9315:3"/> Religion, haue afterwards gotten better inſpirations, and acknowledged their faults, and haue taken their Refuge to Our Clemencie and Bountie, by their moſt humble Petitions, which they haue ſent vnto Vs by expreſſe Deputies, deſiring Vs to graunt them pardon, and to aboliſh the memorie of all things paſt, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue &amp; hold them hereafter as Our other loyall Subiects, in Our favour and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Wee inclining alwayes rather to Clemencie and Mercifulneſſe, then to goe on with rigour, and Our iuſt Armes; Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, that Wee haue advanced much by the ſame, and were likely to get more.</p>
               <p>And having regard vnto their ſubmiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and duties, and being deſirous to ſettle the Peace in Our Kingdome, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnite all our Subiects in Amitie and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord amongſt themſelues, and to cauſe a generall and vniforme Obeyſance to Vs, and for other weightie reaſons and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations moving Vs therevnto. With the adviſe of the <hi>Princes, Dukes, Peeres,</hi> Officers of Our Crowne, and the principall
<hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellers</hi> 
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:9315:3"/> of Our State. We haue ſayd, orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and declared, We ſay, ordayne, and declare by theſe Preſents, ſigned by Our owne hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>We will and are pleaſed;</head>
               <div n="1" type="article">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>THat the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſecret Articles which are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred in Our Courts of Parliament, ſhall be kept in good fayth to Our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of the Pretended Reformed Religion in all poynts, as they haue well and duely enioyed the ſame in the time of the late King Our moſt honoured and renowned Lord and Father (whom God abſolue) and likewiſe ſince Our comming to the Crowne, vntill theſe troubles happened.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="article">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>THat the exerciſe of the Catholike Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike, and Romaine Religion ſhall be ſettled &amp; eſtabliſhed in all places and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters within this Kingdome, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries vnder Our obeyſance, where it hath ceaſed, and be there freely and peaceably continued without any trouble, forbidding <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="article">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:9315:4"/>
                  <p>authoritie, and ſhall willingly open the gates vnto Vs, ſhall enioy the contents of this Declaration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="article">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>VVE expreſly forbid herewithall Our Subiects of the pretended reformed Religion all kind of generall and particular Aſſemblies, circuits, Counſels, leſſer Synods and all other of what qualitie ſoever they may be, vpon paine of high Treaſon, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thay haue an expreſſe permiſſion of vs: being onely permitted vnto them the meetings at their Conſiſtories, Colloquies, and Synods, for meere Eccleſiaſticall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, expreſly prohibiting them to treate of any politike affayres, vpon the penaltie aforeſayd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="article">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>OVr aforeſaid Subiects of the pretended Reformed Religion, ſhall be diſcharged of all acts of Hoſtilitie, of all generall and particular Aſſemblies, circuits, and of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things generally, being contained in the Articles 76. &amp; 77. of our Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> ſince the firſt of <hi>Ianuary.</hi> 1621. vntill this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: therein not comprehending the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable <pb n="9" facs="tcp:9315:4"/> caſes which are ſpecified, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the 86. Article of the ſayd Edict, of which the Iudges may determine as the matter ſhall require if any complaine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="article">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>ANd concerning that which is happened at the Towne of
<hi>Privas,</hi> We will it to be aboliſhed particularly to the Inhabitants of the ſayd place, and likewiſe to the Lord of <hi>Briſon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="article">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>ANd for thoſe which are accomptable, &amp; other Officers touching the dealings of their charges, the Articles 78. and 79. of the ſayd Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> ſhall bee entierly kept and obſerved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="article">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>ANd particularly concerning the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; Sentences given againſt thoſe of the ſayd Religion which haue borne Armes, they ſhall be diſcharged thereof ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Articles 58. &amp; 59. and
60. of of the ſayd Edict. So likewiſe Wee haue ſtrengthened &amp; confirmed, We ſtrengthen and confirme the Iudgements given by the Councells and Iudges, eſtabliſhed by the <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="authentication">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9315:5"/>
                  <p>to be made in what maner ſoever. We charge Our Procurators or Atturnies Generall, and their Subſtitutes to ſet hand thereunto and to vſe to the ſame effect all their beſt endevours and aydes required vnto the ſame. For ſuch is Our pleaſure. In witneſſe whereof, We haue cauſed Our Seale to be affixed on theſe preſents. Given in the Campe before <hi>Mompellier,</hi> the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene day of October, in the yeare of Grace 1622. and of Our Raigne the thirteene.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>It was Signed <hi>Lewis,</hi> And lower by the Kings Commaund <hi>de Lomenie.</hi>
                     </signed> Then ſealed with yeallow waxe vpon a double tayle.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="Edict_of_Nantes">
            <div type="preamble">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9315:5"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>OVIS par la grace de Dieu Roy de France et de Nauarre. A tous ceux qui ces preſentes lettres verront, Salut. Comme tout Prince Chreſtien et craig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Dieu doit auoir en horreur l'effuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> du ſang de l'homme crèe a l'image du tout puiſſant, auſsi eſt il tenu et obligè non ſeulement d'euiter les occaſions de guerre ciuile et domeſtique pour revnir et faire viuxe ſes ſubiects ſous les loix de l'Eſtat en bonne concorde et obeiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance; la meſme bontè Diuine qui a cognu no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre coeur, depuis quil luy à pleu nous appeller au re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gime et gouuernement de ceſte monarchie Francoiſe, eſt Iuge de noſtre interieur: Et chacun ſçait auſsi que nos armes ont eſté autant iuſtes que forcèes et neceſſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res pour le ſouſtien et defence de noſtre Authoritè; ſoit contre ceux qui du commencement ſous diuers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textes empruntes, ont excitè le trouble durant noſtre minoritè, ou depuis contre nos ſubiects ſaiſans pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion de la Religion Pretendue Reformeè, abuſes et ſurpris de l'artifice d'aucuns d'iceux, qui ont cuidè profiter autant de lour ſimplicitè, que de la diuiſion publique de noſtre Royaume; ores que noſtre inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion n'ait iamais eſtè autre (a l'exemple des Roys nos prediceſſeurs d'heureuſe memoire) que de les mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nir en bonne paix et vnion dans le deuoir et obeiſſance qui nous eſt deüe ſous le benefice de nos Edits, et de les traicter comme nos bons et fidelles ſubiects, quand</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <div n="2" type="article">
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:9315:6"/>
                  <p>de leurs benefices et tous autres droits le deuoire que leur apartiennent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="article">
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <p>Comme auſſi l'exercice de la Religion pretendue Reformée ſera reſtabli aux lieux ou il eſtoit ſuiuant noſtre Edit, declarations et conceſſions: et les ſieges de Iuſtice, burauex de recepte, et officiers de finances ſeront reſtablis en meſme eſtat es villes ou ils eſtoyent eſtablis auant ces derniers mouuemens: hormis la chambre de Nerac qui ſera eſtablis en tel lieu que nous auiſerons bon eſtre; apres auoir entendu les remonſtrances des Deputes de noſtre prouince de Guyenne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="article">
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <p>Voulons auſſi que toutes fortifications nouuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, des villes places chaſteaux et fortereſſes tenues par nos dits ſubiects de la Religion pretendue Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formèe, et ſpecialement celles qui ont eſté faites en l'Iſle de Rè et Oleron ſoyent entierement demolies et raçees, demeurans les antiennes, les murailles, tours, portaux, loſſes et contreſcarpes en leur eſtat: auec defence a toutes lesdittes villes de plus forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier de nouueau: et que pour leffect desdites demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, l'oſtages des principaux habitans desdites vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ſeront mis es mains de ceux qui nous plaira d'or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donnér pour lexecution du dit raçement.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="article">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:9315:6"/>
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <p>Afin que les Officiers de noſtre couronne ou au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres commiſſaires deputes puiſſent faire executer le contenu cydeſſus ſuiuant les inſtructions qui leur en ſeront données, entendons que toutes les villes de ladite Religion pretendue Reformèe qui dans quinze iours apres la publicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> des preſentes ſe ſoumettront a noſtre obeiſſance, et nous ouuriront volontairement les portes, ioüiſſent du contenu de la preſente decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="article">
                  <head>6.</head>
                  <p>Defendons tresexpreſſement a nosdits ſubiects de la Religion pretendue Reformée toutes ſortes d'Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleés generales et particulieres, cercles, conſeils, abredges de Synodes, et toutes autres de quelques qualites quelles puiſſent eſtre, a peine de crime de leze maieſte, s'ls n'ont expreſſe permiſſion de nous: ains ſeulement leur ſont permiſes les aſſembleés des Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtoires, Colloques, Synodes, pour pures affaires Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtiques, auec inhibitions treſexpreſſes, dy traiter d'aucune affaire politique, ſur les peines que deſſus.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="article">
                  <head>7.</head>
                  <p>Demeureront auſſi noſdits ſubiects de la Religion pretendue Reformeé, decharges de tous actes d'ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilite, de toutes aſſemblées generales et particulieres, cercles, abredges, et de toutes autres choſes generale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment quelconques contenues es Articles 76. et
77.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="authentication">
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9315:7"/>
                  <p>executer it content
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nons mandemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> les geus tenans nos cours de
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> l'Edit, Baillifs, Seneſchaux, ou leues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> touts autres nos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ciers et officers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> des, queces pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ils facent
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trer chacun en d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ſoy, et le con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> der et obſeruer inuiolablement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> teneur ſans y contreuenir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y ſouffriry eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> enaucune maniere. Enjoig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> generaux et leurs ſubſtituts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> faire pour ceſt effect toute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> inſtances <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> requiſitions neceſſaires, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar tel eſt noſtre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> teſmoigne dequoy nous auous fair met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re noſtre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ces preſentes. Donne au camp de Mompell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 19 iour d'Octobre l'an de grace 1622. et noſtre
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> le 13.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signe LOVJS</hi> Et plus bas par le R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> De Lomen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </signed> 
                     <hi>Et ſeeles ſur double queu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e de cire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9315:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
